<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Azimuth1</title>
    <description>Environmental Analytics | See your world more clearly</description>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>A technical overview of our SAR topo implementation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you may have read in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.azimuth1.com/a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/&quot;&gt;preceding post&lt;/a&gt;, the Search and Rescue (SAR) map we are building seeks to combine the vital features of USGS topographic maps with the ease of use, readability, and&lt;!--more--&gt; higher update frequency of a vector tile based map, in addition to providing supplemental data that may prove useful in SAR related work. This follow-up post is meant to further elaborate on the process behind the SAR map’s creation and current status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brief-introduction&quot;&gt;A brief introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-07-sar-topo-tech-notes/VA_Old Rag Mtn_topo_thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;To start things off, I love the old USGS topographic maps. I love their style. I have a 1984 Old Rag quadrangle hanging above my desk. Those older USGS topos featured more detailed surface features (e.g. trails and utilities) but are, unfortunately, limited by their age and format. Newer USGS topos are generally in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GeoPDF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GeoPDF&lt;/a&gt;, a format which allows for multiple layers that can be toggled depending on the view you want, all enveloped together in a PDF. This comes with its own advantages, however they do not include some of the more specific features one would want for SAR work, as reviewed in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.azimuth1.com/a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/&quot;&gt;Jason’s post&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, GeoPDF not a particularly lightweight platform. With our SAR topo we hope to take everything that’s great about both the older and newer USGS topographic maps, add in any other data that will prove useful in a search and rescue situation, and provide a fully interactive map that can still be used in offline field situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;picking-a-platform&quot;&gt;Picking a platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we were first exploring possible platforms for this project, we’d started with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt; and their new map design tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/mapbox-studio/#darwin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapbox Studio&lt;/a&gt;. The initial prototype for the SAR map was inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapbox/mapbox-studio-outdoors.tm2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapbox Outdoors&lt;/a&gt; style and source in Studio. However, we ran into two primary issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more data we wanted to incorporate into the map, the less Mapbox Studio seemed suited to our needs. With the wide variety of substantial datasets we’re working with, this project just doesn’t lend itself to efficient use of the Studio model, which is highly suited to rapid, lightweight web map development and styling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mapbox does not currently support combining both remote and local data sources for vector tile source creation and styling via Studio, and for the purposes of this prototype we wanted to create something completely independent of sources that require internet access, to support use in the field by searchers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, Mapbox Studio is a very powerful, and actively evolving design tool. The work we did initially in Studio really provided a foundation for how we decided to move forward with the project. Using both the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; data and the supplemental SAR data we’d compiled for styling in Studio, we created an &lt;code&gt;.mbtiles&lt;/code&gt; archive. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/guides/an-open-platform/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MBTiles&lt;/a&gt; is “an efficient format for storing [large vector and raster tilesets] in a single &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sqlite.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt; database.” Once these sources are combined and exported, we can locally host them with relative ease. For this prototype, we’re using a simple &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/&quot;&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt; server for hosting the tiles in concert with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapbox GL&lt;/a&gt;, Mapbox’s OpenGL based vector tile renderer, for the client side rendering. This is further detailed below in &lt;strong&gt;Work Flow&lt;/strong&gt;, followed by an overview of all the different datasets we used in &lt;strong&gt;Data Sources and Layers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-flow&quot;&gt;Work Flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data wrangling. Compiling all of the necessary data from a wide variety of sources.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Running test extracts on OSM data with &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Osmosis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Osmosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Performing any necessary conversions, e.g. converting the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd2011.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Land Cover Data&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.osgeo.org/geotiff/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GeoTIFF&lt;/a&gt; to vector with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gdal.org/ogr2ogr.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ogr2ogr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Additional processing with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.qgis.org/en/site/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt; and Python &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate &lt;a href=&quot;http://postgis.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PostGIS&lt;/a&gt; database for OpenStreetMap data using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openstreetmap/osm2pgsql&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;osm2pgsql&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Currently prototyped with an extract of Virginia, if we continue with this method we will have to expand beyond a locally hosted database to include the rest of the necessary OSM data OR switch to a method which caches tiles from a web based map for offline use, as opposed to 100% local hosting.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine queried OSM data with the additional SAR relevant datasets in Mapbox Studio.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See &lt;strong&gt;Data Sources and Layers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Export vector tileset from Studio for self-hosting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locally host the .mbtiles archive via Node.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The process for setting up a simple Node server for viewing the vector tile set is based on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.stackexchange.com/questions/125037/self-hosting-mapbox-vector-tiles&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GIS StackExchange thread&lt;/a&gt;. It incorporates the node modules &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/express&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/tilelive&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TileLive&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/mbtiles&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mbtiles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Render and style map with Mapbox GL.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prototyped in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/guides/style-manual/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CartoCSS&lt;/a&gt; within MapBox Studio, rewritten in the Mapbox GL JSON structure.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Note: Having gone through the process of rewriting all of my Mabox Studio styling in JSON for Mapbox GL, I’d be very interested in seeing a tool for the conversion between the Studio and GL styling languages. I know it’s not a perfect “one-to-one” conversion in that they are pretty different systems, but it still seems like a gap in the Mapbox workflow. Maybe this will be filled by the new Mapbox GL Design tool, which is currently in beta.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This vector tile rendering utility can be contained within a single local Javascript utility, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nwjs/nw.js/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NW.js&lt;/a&gt;, for simple offline use.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The Virginia prototype takes up just under 3 GB, easy to store a flash drive.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-sources-and-layers&quot;&gt;Data Sources and Layers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;United States elevation contours, Source: &lt;a href=&quot;ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/Elev/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;USGS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;USGS Hydrogeography dataset, Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://nhd.usgs.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;USGS NHD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;National Land Cover Database 2011, Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrlc.gov/index.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MRLC&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exploring more recent vector datasets for this.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roads, trails, transportation infrastructure, and building footprints, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More detailed and regularly updated than comparable USGS data.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;United States interstate and intrastate natural gas pipelines, Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eia.gov/maps/layer_info-m.cfm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EIA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;United States local natural gas infrastructure, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Note: Collected as a supplement to the smaller scale, national level EIA dataset, queried as &lt;code&gt;man_made=pipeline&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;location!=underground,underwater&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;United States power lines, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Note: No declassified national power infrastructure dataset exists, queried from OSM as &lt;code&gt;power=line&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;power=minor_line&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visual buffer around utilities to show potential cleared canopy around power lines, gas lines, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelter locations, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Query includes all features &lt;code&gt;amenity=shelter&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;shelter_type!=public_transport&lt;/code&gt; (e.g. bus shelters, covered train platforms). Unfortunately there are a large number of shelter features that do not include the &lt;code&gt;shelter_type&lt;/code&gt; tag.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can see a full listing of all the shelter sub-types in OSM &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Key:shelter_type&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to features included under &lt;code&gt;amenity=shelter&lt;/code&gt;, there are a number of other tags that could contain shelters relevant to SAR: e.g. &lt;code&gt;tourism=wilderness_hut&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tourism=alpine_hut&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;building=hut&lt;/code&gt;. For the most part features with these more specific IDs are also tagged with &lt;code&gt;amenity=shelter&lt;/code&gt;, and those outliers were mostly private residences or paid lodging (at least within the US). Another potentially relevant shelter tag was &lt;code&gt;shelter_type=rock_shelter&lt;/code&gt;, unfortunately though there are no features currently tagged as such in the US (I guess I’ll have to start mapping those on my hikes).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emergency Medical Services and Fire Stations, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Query includes all features &lt;code&gt;amenity=clinic&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;amenity=doctors&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;amenity=hospital&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;amenity=veterinary&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;amenity=rescue_station&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;amenity=fire_station&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Churches, frequently used for Incident Command Post (ICP), Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Query includes all features &lt;code&gt;amenity=place_of_worship&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mountains and other topographic highs, Source: OpenStreetMap.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Query includes all features &lt;code&gt;natural=peak&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elevation from OSM is included in label.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can view the map below and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sandlot.azimuth1.net/FIND/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe class=&quot;mapfembed rofw cofntainer&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;380&quot; src=&quot;http://sandlot.azimuth1.net/FIND/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allodwfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;as-it-stands&quot;&gt;As it stands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still quite a few things to work on with this prototype, beyond improving general performance: there’s a whole lot to be done with the dynamic labeling, we need to add airport information (e.g. runways, boundaries, etc), distinguish dirt roads from paved roads with more distinctive styling, add styling for mines and caves, add pattern overlay for wetlands, update the land cover data, and refine a few of the OSM queries, just to name a few. Blue contour lines over snow or ice cover have been suggested, as well as differentiating between tree canopy type (e.g. deciduous vs coniferous). Please let us know of any additional features you feel could be potentially helpful to SAR efforts that you’d like to see included in the map!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: For the purpose of this web demo, a Mapbox API key is used for access to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-style-spec/#glyphs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glyphs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-style-spec/#sprite&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sprites&lt;/a&gt;. At the moment I’m exploring a few of the tools in Mapbox’s repo for storing this information locally for offline use, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapbox/fontnik&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fontnik&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapbox/node-fontnik&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;node-fontnik&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapbox/spritenik&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;spritenik&lt;/a&gt;. However, I recently learned that Mapbox GL is working towards using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/HarfBuzz/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HarfBuzz&lt;/a&gt; for this, which would render local storage for font rendering unnecessary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/sar-topo-tech-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/sar-topo-tech-notes.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Designing a topo map for search and rescue</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A child is lost in the forest.  An elderly dementia patient wanders away from home.  A hiker is overdue from a weekend outing.  These scenarios happen daily around the world and wilderness search and rescue teams are called in to find&lt;!--more--&gt; that missing person.  Wilderness SAR teams are specially trained to travel in small groups over varying terrain in all weather, day and night. The lives saved by SAR each year owe their safe return to the training, dedication, and compassion of a largely volunteer SAR response across the globe.  The mission of finding lost individuals often starts on a map.  Maps are used to find likely places where the lost person may have stopped, lost their way, or tried to reach, and so are used to prioritize search tasks for a search mission.  The same map is used in the field as team leaders navigate their way through the task, delineating which areas they have searched and where they have not.  A good map is critical to this accurate accounting of the search effort to ensure that the entire area is being covered appropriately. In the United States, the map most often used for search missions is the US Geological Survey (USGS) &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrangle_%28geography%29&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;7.5 minute series topographic map&lt;/a&gt;.  These maps have a long history of exhaustive work and meticulous detail that went into each map revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;then-usgs-updated-their-maps&quot;&gt;Then USGS updated their maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, the USGS began changing the style and delivery of their topo maps under the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://nationalmap.gov/ustopo/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;US Topo&lt;/a&gt; program.  As changes in our environment appeared more rapidly, the USGS sought to streamline their map production process to increase production, save time, money, and labor. Several tradeoffs were made that impacted the usefullness of these maps for SAR purposes. The new US Topo map style has several cartographic improvements for readability on digital devices, and they are delivered in more flexible layered PDF files rather than fixed raster images.  However, many important features were removed or degraded that can impact the ability of SAR teams to accurately navigate and ensure that they have covered an area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new contour lines are algorithmically generated from digital elevation data rather than from manual photogrammetry.  Faster, cheaper, but lacks details for precise navigation in microterrain &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row row-centered mar2&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Pre-2009 Raster Contours&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_old1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Current Vector Contours&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_new1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utility lines, like trails, are often used by lost persons to travel.  They are an important feature for search task planning and navigating in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row row-centered mar2&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Pre-2009 Raster utilities&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_old2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Current Vector maps without utilities&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_new2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trails were removed from the new US Topo series - a critical feature to know about for search and rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row row-centered mar2&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Pre-2009 Raster trails&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_old3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Current Vector maps without trails&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/USGS_new3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buildings were removed from the new US Topo series.  They just change much faster than the topo map series are updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row row-centered mar2&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Pre-2009 Raster buildings&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/usgs-bldg-old.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col-xs-6 col-centered pad0&quot;&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt;Current Vector maps without  buildings&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/usgs-bldg-new.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-we-made-a-new-topo-map-for-search-missions&quot;&gt;So we made a new topo map for search missions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azimuth1 is part of a team working on support tools for first responders formed by Robert Koester of &lt;a href=&quot;http://dbs-sar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dbS Productions&lt;/a&gt;, a long time lost person behavior researcher and publisher for SAR related topics. The work is supported by the First Responder Group within the DHS Office of Science and Technology. Azimuth1 is providing the tech strategy and design component of the program and among other things, we are undertaking an effort to improve the existing topo map to better support search missions.  We’ve supplemented the USGS data with features available from the OpenStreetMap database, and other open source licensed data, that could be integrated into a topo map tailored for SAR use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we added back the useful features that USGS had to remove &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trails&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-contour.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utilities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-utility.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buildings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-bldg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since USGS strives for equal data coverage across the whole United States, it would not include a dataset of trails in a single state, even if it was very good. Our approach is just the opposite. If we can include only one item listed as ‘culvert’ and that culvert is useful to a particular missing person search then it’s useful to put on our map.  In other words, we don’t require that we show &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; culvert before we show &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; culvert.  The mapping of these detailed features varies widely across the country. But in places where volunteers have taken the time to map and verify detailed feature data, it is extremely valuable to searchers in that area.  This is exactly why OpenStreetMap is such a valuable dataset for custom mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;features-for-sar&quot;&gt;Features for SAR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we added map features that were specifically chosen to help searchers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical&lt;/strong&gt; - local doctors, and other EMS - medical support in the event of an injury or when the lost person is found and needs medical attention.  Search dog handlers will now see any known veterinarian offices from their task map and planning maps.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-hospital.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Churches&lt;/strong&gt; - often used as areas to set up base operations and staging areas for volunteers to rest and eat. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-church.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aquaducts&lt;/strong&gt; - feature where finds are often made. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-aquaduct.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shelters&lt;/strong&gt; - possible waiting area for overdue subjects, and navigation points. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/2015-06-02-a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives/sar-shelter.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can access the new SAR map below and at &lt;a href=&quot;http://sandlot.azimuth1.net/FIND/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. Right now, we’re just hosting the state of Virginia (our home state) but will have the whole US available very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SAR folks! Please give us your feedback and ideas to make this map more helpful in saving lives outdoors.   And look for our next post in this series where we detail the data, technology, and processing used to create these maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;test-drive-our-topo-for-the-state-of-virginia&quot;&gt;Test drive our topo for the state of Virginia&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;mapembed&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;380&quot; src=&quot;http://sandlot.azimuth1.net/FIND/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOOTNOTES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small em&quot;&gt;This article was originally submitted for presentation at &lt;a href=&quot;http://stateofthemap.us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;State of the Map US&lt;/a&gt; 2015 in NYC
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To which everyone says “So use GPS and you get that precision back.”  Which is partly true, but even with the growth of GPS and GIS in SAR operations, there are still some real deficiencies.  Getting high quality maps onto GPS units is difficult.  Handheld units typically require expensive map upgrades or a complex series of steps to update your own map data.  Mobile phone GPS apps have the ability to display high quality maps, but require precaching of maps before going in the field since mobile coverage isn’t usually available.  Then there’s the issue of battery life.  Constant navigation over a 6-10 hour task would deplete most phone batteries.  Extra capacity battery cases, rechargers, solar chargers, etc just add to the already significant weight of gear carried by most field searchers.   Then there’s the logistics of getting GPS track data back onto a central map at search base.  Without wifi, compliant software, etc, there are just too many possible devices and connections for a thinly staffed search base to accommodate most possibilities.  The future of mobile mapping in SAR is coming, but right now it stands on the weak shoulders of battery life and interoperability.  Then there’s the issue of training.  If a team leader loses or breaks a GPS unit, we don’t want them to be out of commission until a new one can be found.  The essential skills of precise land navigation with map and compass will be in our forseeable future, so we want to provide a map that searchers deserve. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There aren’t any up to date sources of the high precision contour lines available to our knowledge, so we haven’t been able to replace the contour lines.  The new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geo-airbusds.com/worlddem/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WorldDEM&lt;/a&gt; high resolution elevation data for the globe from Airbus that is coming available now might make the high resolution contours possible again. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/a-new-topo-map-for-saving-lives.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>